A Guide to the Booth Tarkington Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Letters to and from Booth Tarkington
    - 1942 January 24"Pratt" [Henry Pratt Smith?] to Booth Tarkington, thanks him for his letter, appreciates that the coast is well protected and thinks that hunting for subs with depth bombs would be a more interesting and exciting sport than hunting whales; he also gives his assessment of the state of the war, expecting Hitler to revamp and dash off to Africa through Spain and Portugal, and through Turkey to the Dardanelles to grab the Mediterranean; discusses the debate about whether it will be more effective to tackle the Pacific or Europe first; worries if the Axis powers are able to take control of the Philippines, Singapore and the Dutch East Indies, since that could prolong the war by at least five years, concluding: "All that we can do is to hope, keep our chins up and trust that a reorganization of those in charge of our production in Washington will bring about a situation where maximum results may be obtained. I consider it quite an accomplishment for Mr. Big [F.D. Roosevelt?] to do as he should have done a year or a year and a half ago, appoint one competent individual at the head of our defense program, which I think is the most encouraging step that has been taken, but whether or not he will keep hands off is still somewhat problematical, and if we could get Mrs. Big to retire gracefully from her continuous and irritating activities, we would be still better off.", TLS, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:37)
    - 1943 March 19[Walter Moses] to Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, with news clipping, Moses, a classmate of Tarkington while at Princeton, in the Class of '95, thanks him for his letter to the City Council of Indianapolis urging the rescue of stray dogs by the establishment of a downtown municipal pet shop where stray dogs will be sold for four dollars. Tarkington's letter first appeared in The Indianapolis Star, March 16, 1943, under the caption "Tribute to Man's Friends.", TLS, carbon copy, 1 page (Box-folder 1:38)
    - 1943 March 25 Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, to Walter Moses, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, expresses his obligation to his dogs and those of Mr. and Mrs. Moses, because his letter about stray dogs has brought a letter from an old school friend, TLS, 1 page, with envelope (Box-folder 1:39)
    - 1943 October 14 Booth Tarkington, Kennebunkport, Maine, to Elizabeth Trotter, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, sends news about Kennebunkport, the C.G. dinner and celebration, an explanation about the gift of a pair of amber bottles as tokens of birthday esteem from Booth and his wife, Susanah Keifer Robinson Tarkington, news of Betty, and a story about Miss L. Keifer being threatened by boys throwing rocks at his front terrace and about 75 or 80 gray squirrels "trying nobly to hit her with acorns.", ALS, in pencil, 2 pages on 1 l., with envelope (Box-folder 1:40)
    - 1944 December 13 Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, to Elizabeth Trotter, writes about one of the boys from the area, who was just 19, missing in action; the request by the Army and Navy for everyone not to travel on the trains during the holidays to leave space for the servicemen, so Betty just can't get home if she tried; mentions the gale and great tide and its effect upon Kennebunkport where part of the seawall is down and Scott Campbell's lawn and cellar ran deep with salt water., ALS, in pencil, 2 pages on 1 l., with envelope and a news clipping review on "First Principles of Verse" by Robert Hillyer (Box-folder 1:41)
    - 1945 March 8 Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, to Elizabeth Trotter, writes concerning her observations about his book Image of Josephine, "I'm glad you 'got' the girl in this book… You're off track, though, when you say I give Josephine a mean set of trials; the author doesn't do those things - he's a detached observer of what happens and this ("what happens") grows out of the basic 'situation' and the characters therein inter-engaged. Once that 'situation' is set, the rest is mechanical, can't be interfered with. The clue to Josephine comes late in the book when her opponent, old [?] says 'Fine girl!" He also writes about Susanah's proposed trip to New York in order to accept the Academy's Howells Medal for him for his work since 1940 on May 18th and Mr. Roberts news that it will take an Act of Congress to remove the disgusting mural from the village post office at Kennebunkport., ALS, in pencil, 2 pages on 1 l., with envelope and a news clipping of an article by Booth Tarkington "Shall We Choose Insanity?" from The Indianapolis Star, March 29, 1945 (Box-folder 1:42)
    - n.d. Booth Tarkington to A.C. Hotel, a note in pencil, clarifying his reservations at the hotel, ANS, in pencil, 1 page (Box-folder 1:43)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence concerning Booth Tarkington
    - 1924 October 6 Allan A. Hunter, Wallace Lodge, New York, to Elizabeth Trotter, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, while attending a "retreat" which has proved more a "wrangle" has been busy discussing programs and philosophies for the new social order, with Scott Nearing insisting that a catastrophic class struggle is economically foreordained; and responds to an article by saying it will be a temptation to construct a sermon around "the incident of Lyell Rader and his exploitation of Job." Hunter is also glad that she likes R[upert?] Brooke and he appreciates the humor in her own article, where she reminds him of her sister, ALS, 7 pages on 7 leaves (Box-folder 1:44)
    - 1925 June 5 Henry G. Leach, editor of The Forum, to Elizabeth Trotter, thanks her for all she has done with Booth Tarkington and encourages her to send the "Mad Tea-Party" to Mr. Shaw, saying "He is insulting to even to flattery and this will render him breathless, for five seconds at least.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:45)
    - 1925 June 16 Henry G. Leach, editor of The Forum, to Elizabeth Trotter, writes that he will appreciate anything that she can persuade Tarkington to do to help establish The Forum, and will pay him double the regular rates but cannot yet compete with Curtis and Crowell. Leach writes about what he would like to see from Tarkington, "an essay blowing to bits the inferiority complexes of our young people (by the way, I saw "The Poor Nut" last night and recommend it), or a very short story that would be too short for his regular magazines. Nothing serious at all. We need humor in The Forum and if we get it attached to Booth Tarkington's name, we want it as light as possible.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:45)
    - 1927 July 15 Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, remarks upon the extremely hot weather in Philadelphia and asks about Betty, writing "Tell Betty to plug hard at the story thing. She is the luckiest of girls to have a chance to be coached by the man who wrote Seventeen.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:46)
    - 1927 October 6 Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, tries to arrange a time to visit at Cleeve Gate or to lunch with her in Philadelphia, TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:46)
    - [ca. 1927] July 12 Robert Emmet MacAlarney(1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, mentions the very hot weather in Manhattan, rejoices in the recovery of her dog, recommends J. Forrest as "a perfection of male type for the setting down" to an aspiring lady author; refers to an alleged statement by BT in the newspaper, discounting the trousers paragraph, and also waving aside "the interview in the Manhattan papers which made him refer to The Plutocrat, that we begin printing in the fall, as a poor novel.", TLS, 3 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:46)
    - [ca. 1930] Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, gives his impression of Mirthful Haven by Booth Tarkington in which he felt Tarkington withheld his punches because he was drawing upon the background of Kennebunkport, but still produced a fine book. "More than once Sarah Orne Jewett crept into my mind while I read. Which BT would take as a compliment, I am sure. After all, the true test of any novel is: does the reader dwell in the environment of his page characters as well as feel with them. And somehow, albeit I know mine own fleeting impressions of the spot you love, I now have an impression that I've lived there for moons. The odors, the vistas, the sounds of the rocky coast… they filled a Ghetto living room last night. And can any writer demand more than realization that he wiped off the map for a couple of hours such a horrendous terrain?", ALS, 3 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:46)
    - [1931] Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, remarks upon how much Booth Tarkington is not only respected and appreciated but actually loved by many of his readers; has purchased yet another copy of Seventeen to distribute because he feels it is among the best of his writing, having captured the essence of youth for all time; and says of Tarkington, "He has helped so many of us humans to keep on an even keel. For he has never preached tolerance and understanding - he has radiated it, in, between, and behind his lines. There lies a Sahara desert between preaching and radiating." He also mentions the actor Henry Ainley (1879-1945) and Barton Currie, whose book on collecting is finished., TLS, 3 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:46)
    - [n.y. March] Friday Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, discusses Betty's story under her pseudonym, "I like this story better than anything she has ever done. I mean that. It has more sediment style. She has made Mrs. Dale real, and Mrs. D's are not easily made that." He also discusses Prohibition, lists his own beliefs in a Minor Charta of nine points under the broad subjects of Archaeology, Authors, including: Chaucer, Samuel Johnson, Dickens, Rudyard Kipling, and Booth Tarkington; Religions of all stripes; and Cleeve Gate and the mistress thereof; and also sends birthday greetings to William Henry Trotter., TLS, 4 pages on 4 leaves (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Sunday morning Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, writes that he is unable to return to Green Hill until June, has to go to Carlisle and Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, to take care of some matters for his mother, has an engagement in New England to speak to some junior college girls, remarks about the "three recent flying fools" in New York and the ensuing hysteria created by them., TLS, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Good Friday Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, writes about Booth Tarkington "being exploited as he emerges from a ghastly experience. But he is lucky to emerge at all.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Tuesday morning Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, "the news in re BT is stunning. What a joy to know that the third operation is unnecessary! Betty is standing by like a brick. And how much she must be learning. I envy her that chance. The new Penrod stories shall be grabbed when they appear. I have been reading avidly all that came out en magazine. But that is not the right way to read BT. You want him between cloth covers. I still feel that he should do Seventeen-Plus. It's been a fetish of mine, but I can't make BC make him see it.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Wednesday morning Robert Emmet MacAlarney (1873-1944) to Elizabeth Trotter, has torn up Betty's annotated letter concerning Booth Tarkington, saying "Logic would arrange that the worthwhile folk, who have given as well as taken from life, should be insured against unnecessary aches and frustrations." Incomplete letter, TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:46)
    - 1916 September 26 Bet [Miss Elizabeth Trotter] to "Dearest Mussy" [Mrs. William H. Trotter ("Elizabeth")], sends a postcard from Colorado Springs, Colorado,with two little metal burros attached, and writes "Hope you like the little burros. Will see you almost as soon as they - wild to get home to you." (Box-folder 1:47)
    - [ca. 1935?] Bet [Miss Elizabeth Trotter] to "Dearest Mussy" [Mrs. William H. Trotter ("Elizabeth")], sends another copy of a letter by [Booth Tarkington] for her to read, promises to return the letter about Epernon [of Old France?], will wire the time of the arrival of the train, and describes a [pet?] container they will use on the train, TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:47)
    - [1938 October 6] Bet [Miss Elizabeth Trotter] to "Dearest Mussy" [Mrs. William H. Trotter ("Elizabeth")], her letter received but not read to Tarkington yet, encloses a copy of a letter Tarkington has written to Warrack Wallace, and still cleaning the floats and gangway at Seawood, Kennebunkport, Maine, ALS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:47)
    - [1938] Bet [Miss Elizabeth Trotter] to "Dearest Mussy" [Mrs. William H. Trotter ("Elizabeth")], encloses a copy of Mr. Coffee's classic cultural address and some copies of an item in Variety, "Interesting as yet another example of the trickiness of the New Dealists. Not much they don't stoop to." She also writes about finding mold on the inner pages of manuscripts in the most expensive and modern type of filing cabinet that is supposed to secret moisture in case of a fire, now she has to go over and wipe each page, laying them to dry separately, discusses the health of [Figaro?] the dog, and mentions that Tarkington has gone out to "a man's dinner" that he did not want to attend., ALS, 3 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:47)
    - [1938] Bet [Miss Elizabeth Trotter] to "Dearest Mussy" [Mrs. William H. Trotter ("Elizabeth")], encloses copies of correspondence, mentions Tarkington's letter to Mr. Ludlow, their Democratic representative in Congress, which included a copy of his previous letter to Coffee, about whom she writes, "In spite of the fine print Mr. Coffee's address is worth reading. It's one of the most pathetically comic documents I've ever read - the poor culture-posing sap! The Unions ought to try to find a sponsor who can do a leetle bit better.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:47)
    - n.y. April 22 Bet [Miss Elizabeth Trotter] to "Dearest Mussy" [Mrs. William H. Trotter ("Elizabeth")], has just returned from a family dinner at the country club "Woodstock" where Booth and Josephine Jameson were in high spirits and full of tales about their trip to Mexico, "such a nice family - & I longed for you.", ALS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:47)
    - 1940 December 21 A. Warner, Great Britain, to Miss Elizabeth Trotter, "My Dear Betty," Indianapolis, Indiana, sends Christmas greetings, encourages her about her old rheumatic trouble, expresses thanks for the news from Egypt and the Mediterranean where Italy is becoming a grave liability to Hitler, ALS, 2 pages on 1 l., with envelope (Box-folder 1:48)
- Series III: Photographs, Printed and Miscellany
  - 1928 January 16 Bill sent to Mrs. Wm. H. Trotter by L.D. Norton, featuring a caricature of a bird with an extremely long and large bill upon which the bill has been speared, with the note "This fellow is not exactly handsome, but I claim he is some bill collector. Can B classify him?" At the top of the bill is another note, "I sent him $75.00 of my Christmas money. He's the kind I like to help" presumably by Elizabeth Trotter (Box-folder 1:49)
  - 1935 April 19 Contract between Booth Tarkington and the Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Corporation for motion picture rights to "Rennie Peddigoe" (Box-folder 1:50)
  - n.d. Photographs and snapshots, of three young boys (including a tintype and a negative), a golfer, two men on a beach, a young woman, and a sailing ship, all are unidentified but presumably some of the photographs pertain to Booth Tarkington (Box-folder 1:51)
  - Printed Items (10 items in one folder)
    - 1928 January 16 Printed Review of Claire Ambler by Booth Tarkington in Time (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1930 February 20 Printed Advertisement and Mail Order Form for tickets to The Plutocrat a new American comedy by Arthur Goodrich based on the novel of the same name by Booth Tarkington, 2 copies, one without the mail order form attached (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1932 January Printed Book of the Month Club News featuring Mary's Neck by Booth Tarkington (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1933 Printed "Reader's Choice for Christmas" New York Times Recommendation of Presenting Lily Mars by Booth Tarkington (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1937 August Printed News clipping about Booth Tarkington and his career in the column "The Brighter Side" by Damon Runyon, from the Daily Mirror (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1938 August 1-13 Printed Card for the Garrick Players and the Booth Tarkington Drama Festival plus an Exhibition of Tarkingtoniana at Dock Square (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1941 February 13 Printed Bulletin [no number] masthead for Indiana Committee for National Defense, with a news clipping from The Indianapolis Star, dated February 16, 1941, glued on the page as the text for the bulletin and titled, "Statement by Temporary Chairman to Indianapolis Group" (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1941 February 27 Printed Bulletin No. 16 Indiana Committee for National Defense, with mimeographed section (Box-folder 1:52)
    - n.y. August 17 & 18 Printed Advertisement of Princess Obolensky Collection of Hand Quilted Things Made in Kentucky, with a hand-written note "next to the Schooner Regina on the River-road" at Kennebunkport, Maine (Box-folder 1:52)